[SPEAKER_01]: I was listening briefly this morning, the talk, learning how to feel, that one, that you did some time ago, I don't know, kind of more recent.
[SPEAKER_01]: But anyway, in the beginning of it, you were talking about these ideas, it's like, for example, you go into the village and you establish your mind on perceptions of the forest, you're not affected by anything in the village.
[SPEAKER_01]: But I found it difficult to understand that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, because you were not actually in the forest.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thus, you couldn't have established your... Well, if you were in the forest, and your mind got established upon the perception in the forest, then you could quite likely be able to establish yourself still upon those perceptions, even when you cease to be in the forest.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if you haven't been in the forest, and if you haven't established your mind upon the perceptions of the forest, then obviously you can't do that.
[SPEAKER_02]: It would remain on the level of abstraction.
[SPEAKER_02]: And the reason... the reason why perceptions of the forest were in that sutta is because... what is the main difference between a remote wilderness forest and village?
[SPEAKER_02]: What would be the main difference?
[SPEAKER_02]: Less people, less busy... No people.
[SPEAKER_02]: Absence of people.
[SPEAKER_02]: Absence of others.
[SPEAKER_02]: Just like the main characteristic of the... if you establish your mind upon the perceptions of the forest, means no others.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then you stay established upon that perception when you go among others.
[SPEAKER_02]: And if you remain established, obviously, then nothing that comes from others can invade you, can invade your mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: I suppose I'm not understanding how one can remain established on a perception of no people when there are people.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, well, the mind can.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because people, all it implies, absence of them, as a possibility.
[SPEAKER_02]: When you actually went into the actual experience of that possibility of absence of people, you kind of had it validated.
[SPEAKER_02]: You've been dwelling in, you've been living in.
[SPEAKER_02]: You got used to it, you started discerning signs and tokens of such perceptions.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then you go on people, and you remain established upon the entire count, like the complete counter-part.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you don't have to go to the forest to become an arahant, but it is certainly quite a suitable way to develop a mind, which is why the Buddha was so encouraging about it.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that was the purpose as well.
[SPEAKER_02]: Forest means no others.
[SPEAKER_02]: You don't run away from them because they bother you, you fear them, or whatever.
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: You go there to develop such perceptions, so that then, when you're surrounded by people, it won't make a difference.
[SPEAKER_02]: Sometimes people use this go-to-forest because they don't want to have to deal with anything.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, they feel like, oh, I'm boring, I run away.
[SPEAKER_02]: But it is nothing to deal with, eh... with others, involving others, although it would be great.
[SPEAKER_02]: But that's... that's a completely wrong basis for doing such thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the perceptions we're referring to is like how... how it is that I know that I'm in a forest, as opposed to how I know I am in a city, which is namely the absence of various things in the forest.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, so, maybe the confusion is kind of like, what does it mean to establish the mind on perception?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: I think that is spoken of in another talk, where the mind is not established, then it's an abstraction.
[SPEAKER_02]: If the mind actually matches the level of that phenomenon, then it ceases to be abstraction.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's where the mind is established upon it, upon such notions.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I'll have to definitely revisit that talk.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just not really clicking for me, like, how you can have establishments of perceptions of something that is not directly present.
[SPEAKER_01]: Being perceived.
[SPEAKER_02]: But that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: As I said, perceptions, they tend to the senses, but also to the mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thoughts are being perceived.
[SPEAKER_02]: Perceived sense.
[SPEAKER_02]: Mano, and its counterpart, dhammas, images.
[SPEAKER_02]: So that's the main point.
[SPEAKER_02]: Based on perceptions that you have, like your eyes, ears, nose,
[SPEAKER_02]: You start discerning more general perceptions, possibilities of such perceptions and so on, which are all obviously on the level of the mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why it's the establishment of the mind, not the establishment of the eye or ear.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's the main thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, absence of people, it's always present on the level of mind when you're looking at people, when you're surrounded by people, when your eyes see people.
[SPEAKER_02]: As a remote possibility to that which is on the mental level, it's the absence of these very people.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's where the mind gets established.
[SPEAKER_02]: So that's how you can look at people, while the mind is established on the counterpart of the absence of people.
[SPEAKER_02]: You're not denying that they're not real.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, they're very real, but the mind does not descend on the level of the eye.
[SPEAKER_02]: It stays established upon the images, perceptions that it has developed while in the forest.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then it recognizes, as in that sutta,
[SPEAKER_02]: Now, while I'm established upon this perception of the forest, I can't be bothered by anything in the village, but I can be bothered by changes in the forest.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, then, he expands that and then he establishes his mind upon the phenomenon of earth, an element of earth.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because, again, element of earth as a remote discerned possibility is present in everything.
[SPEAKER_02]: And the mind stays on that, while the experience kind of descends down onto more particular... particularized levels, and it's real.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a little more clear.
[SPEAKER_01]: Actually, all separation that I think is important to clarify is, what is the difference?
[SPEAKER_01]: Let's just stay with the forest, in versus the town.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I'm in town trying to dwell on perceptions of the forest.
[SPEAKER_01]: What's the separation between that and just kind of like not paying attention, daydreaming that I'm in the woods?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, that's when the mind ceases to be established and then it becomes just daydreaming of being in the woods.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's a matter of, at that moment, I might be attending to the woods in a particular kind of way, instead of...
[SPEAKER_02]: If the mind is established, then it's you properly attending to the perceptions of the absence of people in the woods.
[SPEAKER_02]: If the mind is not, then, yeah, that is just fantasy.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, it won't be establishment.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, you will not be impenetrable by the things, perceptions that occur in the city or the village.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's when the mind... Like, you can still be kind of revolving around the same mental images, but the mind is not developed in regard to them.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not established in regard to them.
[SPEAKER_02]: The mind has descended down where the eye is, where the ear is, nose and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: The idea of having the mind on a quote-unquote higher level made a little bit more sense to me.
[SPEAKER_01]: The idea that you can be, you know, talking to people while at the same time the mind doesn't necessarily have to get...
[SPEAKER_02]: Disturbed.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, disturbed by that.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not an easy thing, but it's a thing you can understand being part of.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's what my development is, in the suttas.
[SPEAKER_02]: Samādhi.
[SPEAKER_02]: And all the other, like, well, he establishes his mind by perception of light, right?
[SPEAKER_02]: Infinite space.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's exactly that.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can just take it to various degrees.
[SPEAKER_02]: All the way up to the incessation of perception and feel right.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the same kind of establishment goes into play with like, you know, you just mentioned perception of light, which is typically, you know, the antidote to the third hindrance, soft worker.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's kind of the same idea, you're saying, of establishing the mind and the perception of... Are we talking about light in terms of, like, lightbulb light?
[SPEAKER_02]: Light, a phenomenon of light, which is, in day,
[SPEAKER_02]: Which is in the dark, as the absence.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Which is in the lightbulb, when you can't light.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's the thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: You don't...
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not a particular object that emits light.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not staring into a lightbulb.
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: Or is it staring into clay discs to establish your mind upon the element of earth, which is what people do.
[SPEAKER_02]: They stare at the plexus.
[SPEAKER_01]: On a general level, understanding that there is a phenomenon of light, that implies light,
[SPEAKER_01]: Absence of light, but it's still a one phenomenal light.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Establishing the mind and that in the same way to overcome sleepiness.
[SPEAKER_02]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_02]: Or to not own sleepiness, not indulge sleepiness.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because sometimes the body might be genuinely sleepy.
[SPEAKER_02]: But obviously, if you take it up, then it becomes your sloth in total.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if it's not, then it's just the body's tired.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then you might actually stay awake, because you realize what it is.
[SPEAKER_02]: Or you might sleep a very little.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, you might sleep a lot if the body was really tired, but you won't be sleeping out of indulgence in that sleep and indulgence in that hindrance, because the mind remains established.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right, right.
[SPEAKER_00]: We're writing an attractiveness section, an attractiveness section, looking at all the cassettes.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's the same thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the same body, same thing, that can be regarded in a manner of infatuation, with lust, or can be seen as actually quite repulsive.
[SPEAKER_02]: But because people have an inherent assumption of the value of pleasure, you just always automatically give your attention to the beautiful aspect of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you don't want to think about the body being coarse and gross.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not... it's not nice.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's where the lust develops further.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, the point is not just to stare at corpses or bodily organs in themselves.
[SPEAKER_02]: The point is to see those very things as things that you do regard as beautiful.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, simultaneously, to see them as beautiful, these ugly things, and that will undermine the notion of beautiful.
[SPEAKER_02]: It usually creeps people's mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: Right.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your mind may have wanted to see a bit of the dimension of the outline of the sky.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's exactly the point.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, in beautiful, there is the underlying ugly, because it can be regarded as... there's a possibility of an emotion of ugly.
[SPEAKER_01]: And same, ugly can be regarded as beautiful, in reference to something else.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's just that people's minds get gripped by the notion of beauty, and lust immediately invades it and spreads it further.
[SPEAKER_02]: For an arahant, who is free from lust, kīrimā.
[SPEAKER_02]: This is a beautiful object that he can see through as ugly.
[SPEAKER_02]: This is an ugly object that he can see through as beautiful.
[SPEAKER_02]: Either way, there won't be any lust in between the two, or in regard to the two.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's on a different level, I think.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, yes, yes.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes, absolutely.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not...
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, when there is beautiful, ugly is on the level of possibility of it, which means it's more general.
[SPEAKER_02]: When it's ugly, it's beauty is on the level of possibility.
[SPEAKER_02]: That is simultaneously present.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why the mind can be developed in regard to both.
[SPEAKER_02]: Making the peripheral more present.
[SPEAKER_02]: Discerning the peripheral while... discerning the peripheral of the general ugliness, repulsiveness, in regard to this particular beautiful thing that has arisen.
[SPEAKER_02]: And I think there is another source of that.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's like, which is more ugly or beautiful?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, anyway, I think you can infer it by itself.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you just, as a whole, the world as a whole, your experience as a whole, if you look at it, you'll see, well, there are more ugly things.
[SPEAKER_02]: There are more things that you don't want to look at.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then you realize that you've always been selectively picking these particular things that we found beautiful.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, ugly, by being more general, will always remain like a foundation for beautiful.
[SPEAKER_02]: And all you have to do is remove the lust in regard to beautiful, and then that relationship becomes apparent.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then you, you know, you won't have to be staring at ugly things to remove your lust, because you have removed it.
[SPEAKER_02]: You removed it in regard to beautiful things.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, then it's just, if it's ugly, you know it's ugly.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's beautiful.
[SPEAKER_02]: You know it's beautiful, but again, there is no lasting regard to it, because you know, within that, it's actually quite repulsive.
[SPEAKER_02]: Nothing is worth being lusted after.
[SPEAKER_00]: Do you have the intention to find those unattractive aspects?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, it's that relationship.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because by giving in to the lust towards beautiful, you automatically maintain ignorance, ignoring of the ugly.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because if, if, if ugly and the beautiful are given at the same time, yeah, you will be repelled by both.
[SPEAKER_00]: In terms of 33 parts, it says he reviews his body from the tip of his head to the soles of his feet.
[SPEAKER_02]: Each, each part he reviews, he reviews, he reviews it in relationship to the general notion of body that is regarded as mine, that is regarded as beautiful, as strong, as healthy, as everlasting, as whatever else.
[SPEAKER_02]: He doesn't go through, like,
[SPEAKER_02]: Systematically, just listing organs for the sake of listing organs.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, when he's thinking about the organ of the eye, ear, nose, skin, nails, each of them individually, he thinks in relationship to the body as a whole.
[SPEAKER_02]: Why is it ugly?
[SPEAKER_02]: Which?
[SPEAKER_02]: What do you mean?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, it's ugly because it's impermanent.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why it's repulsive.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why it's suffering.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why it's ugly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, I mean, it's...
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not...
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not lasted after.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not mindless.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not mindless.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's ugly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you're saying, it's not so much a matter of feeling the liver is nasty looking, but it's just not accessible.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's usually what a person will get when he encounters something ugly, something repulsive.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, I don't want this.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you start looking at the liver,
[SPEAKER_02]: I don't want this.
[SPEAKER_02]: In relation to that notion of the body as a general thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's often the problem that people who get with a super-practice in meditation.
[SPEAKER_02]: It would be...
[SPEAKER_02]: In the beginning, they might see the relationship between every individual part, or a dead body, or anything that they're practicing as a contemplation.
[SPEAKER_02]: They might maintain the mindful relationship between the sense of dead body, but that tends to kind of fall out, fall away, and then it just ends up like trying to re-evoke disgust, for the sake of disgust.
[SPEAKER_02]: But that's... that's equally... can be equally misleading.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm trying to think about that pretty girl and be like, oh, she's made of organs.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: She is, but that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: What you want to see, actually, that even you seeing the pretty girl, that which kind of precedes the sight of a pretty girl, is made of those unwanted, unaccessible, disgusting organs.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then there won't be any... any ground left for lust to... to kind of linger on.
[SPEAKER_02]: Neither in regard to the seen, nor in regard to that because of which there is seen, which is the presence of this conscious body here.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it comes back to preceding.
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: Structurally preceding it.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's how, by understanding that, lust becomes impossible.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not knowing that, that's the basis for lust.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's when you refer to Parasat.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not supposed to be there, but it's there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because when I first started reading the Buddhism, you know, there's that one sutta, I think, Manjana Nikaya 119, if you have to name, Mindless Body Sutta, talks about how you could use mindless body to even attain nirvana.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I'm like, how could you do that without the mind?
[SPEAKER_01]: But when you think about the body in this kind of way we're speaking, it makes perfect sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: Absolutely, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's what we meant.
[SPEAKER_02]: This whole world, this whole universe, is contained in this body.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not in the scientific body made of organs, but in this notion of body, this experience of body, which does precede things that I kind of infer from it.
[SPEAKER_02]: The world and the animal world.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: He goes, after the 32 parts of the body, he talks about the corpse sensation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, you look at a body rotting at various stages, and then one says, you think to yourself, just that body is the same.
[SPEAKER_00]: This body will be long.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just like that body is, this body will be.
[SPEAKER_00]: And there's a root, well, it's called seed spark, yeah?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what does that come down to?
[SPEAKER_02]: While you're looking at a decomposing body, you simultaneously regard this body as that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not as a level of a mental exercise, inference or so on, but basically by seeing, while I'm seeing this, this is that nature.
[SPEAKER_02]: This body shares that very nature.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then the last is removed.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if it's not seen at the simultaneous, on the simultaneous level, so to speak, then it's not done properly, that contemplation.
[SPEAKER_00]: This external, this external body, same as the external.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, the external body that's decomposing, it's basically the nature of that, is the nature of this, which I regard as my internal body.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thus, this internal body is basically like that external body.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thus, whether it's internal or external, both internal and external, the body is there of such nature.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you remove any, well, ignorance in regard to it, and consequently, obviously, desire and lust.
[SPEAKER_02]: They would be lingering around the notion of pleasant and beautiful.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you're saying desire and lust, you mean that, like, in the most broad...
[SPEAKER_01]: In the most broad sense.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not exactly lust.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Just like people have desire and lust in regard to their own body, because they pursue sight, sound, smell, taste, touches, which means you're maintaining the basis of those things, which is your very body, your senses.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thus, those things are on fire as well.
[SPEAKER_02]: Everything is caught up by the fire of lust.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's why, because you're dependent on the beautiful sights, your life revolves around it, you'll be terrified of the notion of losing your eyes.
[SPEAKER_02]: You figure out, if I go blind, you know, equals death.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, just think about the diseases you could have.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Different things that could come your way at any point.
[SPEAKER_02]: Just the fact those things are possible means the body is liable at any time.
[SPEAKER_02]: The fact the body is liable at any time means
[SPEAKER_02]: You're not in control.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because if you were in charge, you would remove that liability.
[SPEAKER_02]: Only something that you cannot control, you cannot own, is liable to things you don't.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thus, it's not yours, for that very reason.
[SPEAKER_02]: But people don't dwell long enough on what body is liable to, to age, get sick and die.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because if they were, they would experience dispassion in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Fear and then dispassion.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, it's dangerous for me to remain regarding this is mine and, like, kind of establishing my entire life around it, can be swept away with a simple illness, next day, and that's it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Falling boulder.
[SPEAKER_02]: Falling boulder, trip over a rock, bitten by a snake, anything.
[SPEAKER_02]: Every heart stop, for no particular reason.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's it, like, there you go.
[SPEAKER_02]: Many people start experiencing anxiety, attacks, whatever, they become aware of that beating heart.
[SPEAKER_02]: In the chest.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because you realize your entire life, everything dear to you, all your hopes, plans, experiences, whatever, depends on this completely independent, simple muscle pump inside of your chest.
[SPEAKER_02]: You have absolutely no way of even in the controlling, of shiputing.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you just can't do anything about it.
[SPEAKER_02]: And if that stops pumping, that's it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Everything
[SPEAKER_02]: It's done.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's kind of swept away with it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, your whole life depends upon something utterly, like a ticking organ, which you can't... you can't even conceive controlling.
[SPEAKER_01]: We have these videos online sometimes, where a person's like at an event, or talking, suddenly they keel over, their brain ends, or... No.
[SPEAKER_01]: ...anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just... like some positional...
[SPEAKER_01]: They're just talking and they just... turn off.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Absolutely.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's like the brain, basically, kind of explodes.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just done.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's the nature of the body in general.
[SPEAKER_02]: I mean, we know, because of the medical science, that, you know, the heart is the kind of dominant pump that maintains and so on, but
[SPEAKER_02]: Overall, it's the nature of any aspect of the body, but it's hardly in control.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's on the same foot.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, whether you regard the heart... That's the unattractiveness, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Whether you regard the heart, contemplate the heart, or the brain, or the body as a whole in general, or just the notion of health and life as a phenomenon, it's all the same thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's the same contemplation that you're removing by simply dwelling on the fact that you cannot be in control, even if you want to.
[SPEAKER_02]: Which means, it's not even possible.
[SPEAKER_02]: To be in control of these things, let alone actually controlling them.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's some practices of, eh...
[SPEAKER_00]: I think it was Arunachala who said to one monk to, like, keep his feces in a jar, when he was thinking about his door from back there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: He wants to destroy it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: But as long as... which, you know, could be helpful for that person at that time.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that can seem to be re-practiced, where you think about the stink, where there's excrement in the air, and those things which generally most people find repulsive.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's another level, assuming that the facts are not controlled.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, if a subha is done rightly, it will lead to the dispassion, which will become... and then it will reveal the nārā.
[SPEAKER_02]: This is really nothing but control.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, a subha done rightly brings the clarity.
[SPEAKER_02]: And clarity of understanding, which is understanding that you're not in control.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not a... not a disgust?
[SPEAKER_02]: Not a disgust, and not like, oh, you do a subha when you need to cancel the lust.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, you need to cancel the lust, because you haven't uprooted the lust.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you don't want to revolve around just constantly managing the lust when the lust arises.
[SPEAKER_02]: Sure, when the lust arises, you manage it, only so that you can then carry on further and uproot it, so it doesn't arise.
[SPEAKER_02]: And if a subha is done rightly, it will really lead to uprooting it.
[SPEAKER_02]: But most people use it just as a management.
[SPEAKER_02]: And which means they're not using it rightly.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's like the other day, we saw the bones, the meat of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Mmm.
[SPEAKER_00]: Meaty bones.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Carnage.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, you get that sign of that carnage, that meaty... Carnage.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, that's the word.
[SPEAKER_00]: Carnage.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm saying it looks like just butchered by a road accident or something.
[SPEAKER_02]: Butchered.
[SPEAKER_02]: Destroyed.
[SPEAKER_02]: Shattered.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's what's... And that's what this body is.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's what dog's body is.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's what our body is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Everything.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, that's it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's because of that, that there is, as the, as the sūtras say, the conceiver and the perceiver, there is the mistake.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because these things are risen, the senses, the sense organs, are the material things in the world, because of which one perceives and conceives the world.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because, obviously, one perceives and thus conceives with ignorance, with non-discernment, with appropriation.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you can never... that perceiver and conceiver can never access, well, anything bodily, but most obviously cannot access any of the sense bases, because the sense bases are there because of which there are sights, sounds, smells, tastes, touches, and then thoughts in regard to that.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you can't see.
[SPEAKER_02]: Your eye can't see itself as that meaty, fleshy, oily, slimy orbit.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why by seeing other eyes, or other organs, or other material things on the same domain as not yours, you can then discern that this, which is simultaneously present, cannot be seen in the same manner, because it's always, in that sense, it's always internal.
[SPEAKER_02]: Or rather, in that sense, it's always this conscious body.
[SPEAKER_02]: But you can fully discern that it shares the same nature, and thus remove any lust, and desire, and appropriation in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if you expect to see it as sight, sound, smell, taste, touch, you won't.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why people get confused with kind of saḷāyātana in general.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because they're always, in a way, they're negative.
[SPEAKER_02]: Always remain negative.
[SPEAKER_02]: They can only be discerned in regard to the things that are positively arising.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like you can see something and know the eye must be there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: Simultaneous.
[SPEAKER_02]: With the sight.
[SPEAKER_02]: And even the knowledge of the eye is simultaneous with the domain, the knowledge of the domain of the sight.
[SPEAKER_02]: There's no time discrepancy.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: As if sense bases are there and then things fall onto them and you perceive.
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, the perception of forest, as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you haven't, you would have to be in a forest as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if you haven't, you stay in a forest alone.
[SPEAKER_02]: And develop perceptions of the forest.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because once you do that, more often, those perceptions will come.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why we would actually go to the mountains, go to the forest, go to the trees and so on.
[SPEAKER_02]: No others.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because we're actually physically making that effort.
[SPEAKER_02]: You are putting yourself in such an environment and circumstances where these perceptions, the mind will... will adhere to them, eventually.
[SPEAKER_02]: Maybe not the first time, but if you know where you're supposed to look, what tokens, what signs, eh... natural discretion in such an environment, then the mind starts discerning the perceptions of the forest, the perceptions of absence of people, absence of the common basis of loss.
[SPEAKER_02]: Absence of the sense abundance, sense object abundance, the delightful, pleasing, food, taste, smell, the absence of all of that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Things that people usually lust after.
[SPEAKER_02]: Absence of that.
[SPEAKER_02]: You won't find that in the wilderness.
[SPEAKER_02]: Always somebody can go to wilderness and their mind stay in the city.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, but that's...
[SPEAKER_00]: The carefulness...
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it just becomes natural.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because you realize, like, if you make a wrong step, you'll end up flying down the cliff, like when we were coming down the riverbed.
[SPEAKER_02]: It was just... you didn't have to make the effort or practice mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_02]: You were just mindful.
[SPEAKER_02]: You just... every move, every... everything you leaned on, everything you grabbed, everything you put a foot on, you were just mindful.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, you are aware of your body and the afflictions of your body.
[SPEAKER_00]: Basic, you have to look after food, shelter, clothing, warmth, health.
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: And see, those are things that most often people take for granted.
[SPEAKER_02]: If we weren't taking it for granted, you don't... you wouldn't have to go to the remote forests and climb the mountains and so on.
[SPEAKER_02]: But
[SPEAKER_02]: It's so deeply rooted, it's so natural to take these things for granted once you have them, that then, yeah, you need these reminders to realize that actually body, even a healthy, normal body, requires a great deal of maintenance and protection and sheltering, which is actually hard work.
[SPEAKER_02]: But obviously, living in a society, staying in the cities where these things are provided, you just take it for granted because you don't think about it.
[SPEAKER_02]: All you have to do is just remove yourself from that setting and then you realize.
[SPEAKER_02]: What kind of maintenance it is.
[SPEAKER_02]: How exposed the body is.
[SPEAKER_02]: Even, even if it's, you know, even when it's at its peak, it's best.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's still exposed.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's post-tolerance.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's post-tolerant.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you can't say, you can't shelter that.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can't build a house around it.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's a house too.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's out on that level.
[SPEAKER_02]: Or rather, the body is out where that house is as well.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it just remains external.
[SPEAKER_02]: It remains liable to all sorts of things.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you can't change that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Only relatively speaking, like living in a house and sticking on a cloud in this office.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is a sutra, so long enough, I read this morning about the forest.
[SPEAKER_00]: Venerable Nāgīta, American Prasenjit,
[SPEAKER_00]: There's two suttas about Venerable Nāgītā, and he's in the Aṅgudjuna Itāya.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is the one from the sixes.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're both similar in the beginning, but different teachings.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's a lot of different teachings.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is the one in terms of the forest.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, that's the one.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, eh...
[SPEAKER_00]: On one occasion, a blessed one was wandering on tour along the coastlines, together with a large sandal.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, he reached the coastline Brahmin village, eh... named Icchanangala.
[SPEAKER_00]: Always call it Gala.
[SPEAKER_02]: Icchanangala.
[SPEAKER_00]: He said that a blessed one dwelled in Icchanangala.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, a good report about the most... Master Gautama has circulated thus, that this one is an arahant, perfectly enlightened.
[SPEAKER_00]: His teachings... dhamma...
[SPEAKER_00]: He teaches the dhamma that is good in the beginning, good in the middle and good in the end.
[SPEAKER_00]: The right meaning and phrasing reveals a spiritual life that is perfectly complete and pure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, it's good to see such arahants.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, when the night had passed, the Brahmin householders of that town took abundant food of various kinds and went to the forest.
[SPEAKER_00]: They stood outside the entrance making an uproar and a racket.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, on that occasion, the Venerable Nāgita was the Blessed One's attendant.
[SPEAKER_00]: The Blessed One then addressed the Venerable Nāgita.
[SPEAKER_00]: Who is making such an uproar in a racket, Nāgita?
[SPEAKER_00]: One would think it was a fisherman at a haul of fish.
[SPEAKER_00]: The Bhante, these are the Brahmin householders of Ichanamgala, who have brought abundant food of various kinds.
[SPEAKER_00]: They are standing outside the entrance, wishing to offer it to the Blessed One and the Saṅgha of Bhikṣu.
[SPEAKER_00]: Blessed one says, let me never come upon fame, Bhagītā, and may fame never catch up with me.
[SPEAKER_00]: One who does not gain at will, without trouble or difficulty, with bliss of renunciation, bliss of solitude, bliss of peace, bliss of enlightenment, that I gain at will, without trouble or difficulty, might accept that vile pleasure, that slothful pleasure, that pleasure of gain, honor, praise.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is the time for the Blessed One to consent.
[SPEAKER_00]: Wherever the Blessed One will go now, the Brahmin households of
[SPEAKER_00]: He's not concerned.
[SPEAKER_00]: And he goes on to say, here, Nāgītā, I see a bhikkhu dwelling on the outskirts of a village, sitting in a state of compulsion.
[SPEAKER_00]: It then occurs to me, now, a monastery attendant, or a novice, or a co-religionist, will cause that venerable one to fall away from that compulsion.
[SPEAKER_00]: For this reason, I am not pleased with this bhikkhu's dwelling on the outskirts of a village.
[SPEAKER_00]: Compose near the village with a client, because he's near the environment.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because it's basically polluting.
[SPEAKER_02]: Non-composed, sleepy, drowsy, lazy, but in the forest, well, will eventually come out of it, sleepy, drowsy, laziness, and then develop the wrong perception in the forest.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because he does... he still remains physically in the better environment.
[SPEAKER_02]: The state of blindness.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well...
[SPEAKER_02]: The state of oneness, basically, when the mind is established upon a more general thing, it's not diversified among more particular things that you get in the village.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's the state of oneness in relation to that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And not the state of oneness that if you're talking to those who might not see that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Uniformity.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not diversified.
[SPEAKER_00]: I see Nāgītā, a forest-dwelling bhikkhu, sitting in the forest, in an uncomposed state.
[SPEAKER_00]: It then occurs to me, now this Venerable One will compose his uncomposed mind, or guard his composed mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: For this reason, I am pleased with this bhikkhu's dwelling in the forest.
[SPEAKER_00]: I see Nāgītā, a forest-dwelling bhikkhu,
[SPEAKER_00]: Then it occurs to me, now this venerable one will liberate his un-liberated mind, will guard his liberated mind, for this reason I am pleased to speak his dwelling in the forest.
[SPEAKER_00]: I see Nāgita, big with dwelling on the outskirts of the village, who gains robes, alms, food, lodgings, medicines, provisions for the sick, desiring gain, honor and fame.
[SPEAKER_00]: He neglects seclusion, neglects remote lodgings in the forest and jungle groves, having entered the villages, towns and
[SPEAKER_00]: I see Nāgītā, a forester in Bhikkhu, who gains robes, alms food, lodgings, and medicines and provisions for the sick.
[SPEAKER_00]: Having dispelled that game, I am in praise.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yet, I do not neglect seclusion.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yet, I do not neglect remote lodgings in the forest and jungle groves.
[SPEAKER_00]: For this reason, I am pleased as Bhikkhu's guardian in the forest.
[SPEAKER_00]: When, Nāgītā, I am traveling on a highway,
[SPEAKER_00]: Praising first.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, making the effort in terms of not neglecting it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, even if... even if it's not perfect,
[SPEAKER_02]: Even if a person is sleepy and lazy and tired or afraid, still, you still don't neglect it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Sooner or later, you'll come out of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: And the environment is suitable, as we spoke in the previous...
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a great template.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, it's basically like saying, well, he goes into an empty hut, empty dwelling, and says, this place is empty of others.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then he, the same
[SPEAKER_02]: Perception is the same phenomenon that he applies to himself.
[SPEAKER_02]: This is empty of any self.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's there as such, but it's empty of the owner.
[SPEAKER_02]: But you do need, like, you do need that physical incentive, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_02]: Your body needs to be such an environment, so you can have the right inference.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not just, like, to think about it, but never abandon a crowd, or never, never abandon the proximity of the crowd.
[SPEAKER_02]: Obviously, you know, you're not supposed to, and you don't have to, like, run away and hide from people and never see them again.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because if that were the case, well, we would be allowed to store our own food, grow our own food, and live on our market, and never engage with laypeople.
[SPEAKER_02]: But it was clear that no!
[SPEAKER_02]: Living on the fringe, on the outskirts, and then inspiring them either with your lifestyle,
[SPEAKER_02]: Over the teachings, if they want to hear them and so on, it's fine.
[SPEAKER_02]: But don't neglect the seclusion.
[SPEAKER_02]: Don't now, like, forget the remote forest abodes and just 24-7 stay around lately.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's what means village, lay life, city, today, forever.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, when it's there,
[SPEAKER_02]: If it occurs, it's fine, but you don't neglect the counterpart.
[SPEAKER_02]: Now, you can see that for yourself.
[SPEAKER_02]: The more you go to the forest properly, the more you want to go.
[SPEAKER_02]: The longer you want to stay.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because of that, there's a template.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, as you say, dangerous as well.
[SPEAKER_02]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_02]: There is a real danger, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: But having a body is what's dangerous.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not being in the forest.
[SPEAKER_02]: The only reason things in the forest might be dangerous, like the elephant or a leopard, is because you have a body.
[SPEAKER_02]: And the danger will only pertain to you as long as you're taking the body to be yours.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, experiencing the elements,
[SPEAKER_02]: Heat, cold, wind, hardship, endurance, walking up the mountain, climbing up the rocks, running away from an elephant.
[SPEAKER_00]: But not having...
[SPEAKER_02]: Experiencing those things, basically, with the right mindfulness, just keeps hammering in the nature, the main characteristic of having this body.
[SPEAKER_02]: Exposure.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not yours, not in your control.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's out there.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, by going through with it, with the right mindfulness, with the right view, you're removing any lingering lust and notions of conceit or vanity in regard to the body.
[SPEAKER_02]: Even, you know, even if you're not an old crooked man, something like that, you don't have to be.
[SPEAKER_02]: And actually, yeah, if you wait until you're old and crooked, you are bad in the world.
[SPEAKER_02]: You go while you can, so that afterwards, you can... Don't delay.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's set up.
[SPEAKER_00]: The forest might be set up without distraction.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's the ultimate, sort of, difference.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you were to boil it down, that would be the difference, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Others, absence of others.
[SPEAKER_02]: Distraction, non-distraction.
[SPEAKER_02]: Diversified, unified.
[SPEAKER_00]: Explaining that, again, that mosquito is like a tree falling.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's no personal thing against you.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's no personality interaction.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can put personality on a mosquito, but it's out against you, but you know...
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not.
[SPEAKER_02]: It doesn't pertain to that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Completely unknown.
[SPEAKER_02]: Impersonal.
[SPEAKER_00]: Impersonal.
[SPEAKER_02]: Elements, factors, indifference, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Leeches.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's in.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Dhamma, it's also that idea that people let us get out of fatalism with karma.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, everything happens because of karma.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Every single body.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, of course.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not just the nature of the body to get
[SPEAKER_02]: Having a human body happens because of karma.
[SPEAKER_02]: But what happens to a human body, well, is the nature of a human body.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, indirectly, you're responsible to what happens to a human body because you were reborn.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's your responsibility.
[SPEAKER_02]: But accident is a valid reason for things to occur.
[SPEAKER_00]: Circumstance.
[SPEAKER_02]: You are, again, indirectly responsible.
[SPEAKER_02]: Why?
[SPEAKER_02]: Because you remain.
[SPEAKER_02]: In the possession of that human body, that is liable to accidents.
[SPEAKER_02]: They're liable to absolutely random things happening to it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you'll be affected by that for as long as you stay there.
[SPEAKER_02]: You leave it, it doesn't affect you.
[SPEAKER_02]: No problem.